<tool id="gmt_music_bmr_calc-covg-helper" name="gmt_music_bmr_calc-covg-helper">
    <description>
        Uses calcRoiCovg.c to count covered bases per-gene for a tumor-normal pair of BAMs.
    </description>
    <command>
        gmt music bmr calc-covg-helper --final-output-file=$final_output_file  --min-mapq=$min_mapq  --normal-min-depth=$normal_min_depth  --normal-tumor-bam-pair=$normal_tumor_bam_pair  --output-dir=$output_dir  --output-file=$output_file  --reference-sequence=$reference_sequence  --roi-file=$roi_file  --tumor-min-depth=$tumor_min_depth 
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="min_mapq" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="normal_min_depth" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="normal_tumor_bam_pair" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="output_dir" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="output_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="reference_sequence" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="roi_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="tumor_min_depth" format="text" type="data" help="" />

    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="final_output_file" format="text" label="" help="" />

    </outputs>
    <help>
        

**USAGE**

 gmt music bmr calc-covg-helper --roi-file=? --reference-sequence=? --normal-tumor-bam-pair=?
    [--output-file=?] [--output-dir=?] [--normal-min-depth=?] [--tumor-min-depth=?] [--min-mapq=?]


**SYNOPSIS**

General usage:

 ... music bmr calc-covg-helper \
    --normal-tumor-bam-pair "sample-name path/to/normal_bam path/to/tumor_bam" \
    --reference-sequence input_dir/all_sequences.fa \
    --output-file output_file \
    --roi-file input_dir/all_coding_exons.tsv



**REQUIRED ARGUMENTS**

  roi-file
    Tab delimited list of ROIs [chr start stop gene_name] (See Description) 
  reference-sequence
    Path to reference sequence in FASTA format 
  normal-tumor-bam-pair
    Tab delimited line with sample name, path to normal bam file, and path to tumor bam file (See
    Description) 


**OPTIONAL ARGUMENTS**

  output-file
    Output file path.  Specify either output-file or output-directory. 
  output-dir
    Output directory path.  Specify either output-file or output-directory 
  normal-min-depth
    The minimum read depth to consider a Normal BAM base as covered 
    Default value '6' if not specified
  tumor-min-depth
    The minimum read depth to consider a Tumor BAM base as covered 
    Default value '8' if not specified
  min-mapq
    The minimum mapping quality of reads to consider towards read depth counts 
    Default value '20' if not specified


**DESCRIPTION**

    This script counts bases with sufficient coverage in the ROIs of each gene in the given pair of
    tumor-normal BAM files and categorizes them into - AT, CG (non-CpG), and CpG counts. It also
    adds up these base-counts across all ROIs of each gene in the sample, but covered bases that
    lie within overlapping ROIs are not counted more than once towards these total counts.



**ARGUMENTS**


    --roi-file

      The regions of interest (ROIs) of each gene are typically regions targeted for sequencing or
      are merged exon loci (from multiple transcripts) of genes with 2-bp flanks (splice
      junctions). ROIs from the same chromosome must be listed adjacent to each other in this file.
      This allows the underlying C-based code to run much more efficiently and avoid re-counting
      bases seen in overlapping ROIs (for overall covered base counts). For per-gene base counts,
      an overlapping base will be counted each time it appears in an ROI of the same gene. To avoid
      this, be sure to merge together overlapping ROIs of the same gene. BEDtools' mergeBed can
      help if used per gene.

    --reference-sequence

      The reference sequence in FASTA format. If a reference sequence index is not found next to
      this file (a .fai file), it will be created.

    --normal-tumor-bam-pair

      "sample-name path/to/normal_bam path/to/tumor_bam"

    --output-file

      Specify an output file where the per-ROI covered base counts will be written




    </help>
</tool>
