<tool id="gmt_music_cosmic-omim" name="gmt_music_cosmic-omim" version="0.3.0">
    <description>
        Compare the amino acid changes of supplied mutations to COSMIC and OMIM databases.
    </description>
    <command>
        gmt music cosmic-omim --aa-range=$aa_range  --cosmic-dir=$cosmic_dir  --maf-file=$maf_file  --nuc-range=$nuc_range  --omimaa-dir=$omimaa_dir  --output-file=$output_file  --reference-build=$reference_build $show_known_hits $verbose $wu_annotation_headers 
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="aa_range" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="cosmic_dir" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="maf_file" format="maf" type="data" help="" />
<param name="nuc_range" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="omimaa_dir" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="reference_build" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="show_known_hits" format="text" type="data" help="" checked="False" truevalue="--show-known-hits" falsevalue="--noshow-known-hits"/>
<param name="verbose" format="text" type="data" help="" checked="False" truevalue="--verbose" falsevalue="--noverbose"/>
<param name="wu_annotation_headers" format="text" type="data" help="" checked="False" truevalue="--wu-annotation-headers" falsevalue="--nowu-annotation-headers"/>

    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="output_file" format="text" label="" help="" />

    </outputs>
    <help>
        

**USAGE**

 gmt music cosmic-omim --maf-file=? --output-file=? --reference-build=? [--omimaa-dir=?]
    [--cosmic-dir=?] [--verbose] [--wu-annotation-headers] [--aa-range=?] [--nuc-range=?]
    [--show-known-hits]


**SYNOPSIS**

 ... music cosmic-omim \
        --maf-file input_dir/myMAF.tsv \
        --output-file output_dir/myMAF_output.tsv \
        --no-verbose

 ... music cosmic-omim \
        --maf-file input_dir/myMAF.tsv \
        --output-file output_dir/myMAF_output.tsv \
        --omimaa-dir omim_dir/ \
        --cosmic-dir cosmic_dir/ \
        --no-verbose


**REQUIRED ARGUMENTS**

  maf-file
    list of annotated mutations in MAF format (or any file with MAF+annotation headers) 
  output-file
    Output file contains the input file with two columns appended to the end, corresponding to
    cosmic and omim mutation comparisons, respectively 
  reference-build
    Put either "Build36" or "Build37" 
    Default value 'Build37' if not specified


**OPTIONAL ARGUMENTS**

  omimaa-dir
    omim amino acid mutation database folder 
    Default value '/gsc/scripts/opt/genome/db/omim/20110721' if not specified
  cosmic-dir
    cosmic amino acid mutation database folder 
    Default value '/gsc/scripts/opt/genome/db/cosmic/54' if not specified
  verbose
    Use this to display the larger working output 
    Default value 'false' (--noverbose) if not specified
  noverbose
    Make verbose 'false' 
  wu-annotation-headers
    Use this if input MAF contains WUSTL annotation format headers 
    Default value 'false' (--nowu-annotation-headers) if not specified
  nowu-annotation-headers
    Make wu-annotation-headers 'false' 
  aa-range
    Set how close a 'near' match is when searching for amino acid near hits 
    Default value '2' if not specified
  nuc-range
    Set how close a 'near' match is when searching for nucleotide position near hits 
    Default value '5' if not specified
  show-known-hits
    When a finding is novel, show known AA in that gene 
    Default value 'true' if not specified
  noshow-known-hits
    Make show-known-hits 'false' 


**DESCRIPTION**

    This tool looks at the amino acid changes for the given set of mutations and compares the
    genomic coordinates as well as the affected amino acid to the coordinates and amino acids of
    all cancer-specific mutations listed in the Cosmic and OMIM databases. The database files are
    specially prepared for this task and provided with the MuSiC suite. The tool reports various
    types of matches, including matches within "near proximity", where "near proximity" is
    currently defined as a linear DNA distance of 5 bases or 2 amino acids. (This type of matching
    helps to account for the possibility of subtle differences in reported positions for variants
    due to differences in transcript definitions or other things of this nature.) Any site without
    a match in a particular databases is reported as "novel" with respect to that database.

    The output of this script returns each row the original input MAF file with two columns
    appended to the end of each, one column for each of the databases. Also included is a STDOUT
    printout of a summary of what was found in the input MAF. Neither output can be suppressed in
    the current version. The --verbose option is used to display working notes that are useful for
    various purposes in debugging potential MAF problems. The Omim and Cosmic directories must
    point to the output of the downloader, named appropriately, as they don't recognize the OMIM
    database in the raw download format.

    This tool only compares build 36 or build 37 coordinates that are specified in Cosmic to the
    coordinates in your maf file. This is a weakness of the Cosmic database (not all position
    entries are currently available for both builds) that is out of our control.

    In addition to the standard version 2.3 MAF headers, there needs to be two columns appended.
    These column headers in the MAF must be exactly these names in header line in order for the
    tool to find them:

       transcript_name - the transcript name, such as NM_000028
     amino_acid_change - the amino acid change, such as p.E290V




    </help>
</tool>
