<tool id="gmt_music_path-scan" name="gmt_music_path-scan" version="0.3.0">
    <description>
        Find signifcantly mutated pathways in a cohort given a list of somatic mutations.
    </description>
    <command>
        gmt music path-scan --bam-list=$bam_list --bmr=$bmr --gene-covg-dir=$gene_covg_dir --genes-to-ignore=$genes_to_ignore --id=$id --is-executed=$is_executed --maf-file=$maf_file --min-mut-genes-per-path=$min_mut_genes_per_path --output-file=$output_file --pathway-file=$pathway_file --result=$result
    </command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="bam_list" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="bmr" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="gene_covg_dir" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="genes_to_ignore" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="maf_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="min_mut_genes_per_path" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="output_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />
<param name="pathway_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />

    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="result" format="text" label="" help="" />

    </outputs>
    <help>
        

**USAGE**

 gmt music path-scan --bam-list=? --gene-covg-dir=? --maf-file=? --output-file=? --pathway-file=?
    [--bmr=?] [--genes-to-ignore=?] [--min-mut-genes-per-path=?]


**SYNOPSIS**

 ... music path-scan \
  --bam-list input_dir/bam_file_list \
  --gene-covg-dir output_dir/gene_covgs/ \
  --maf-file input_dir/myMAF.tsv \
  --output-file output_dir/sm_pathways \
  --pathway-file input_dir/pathway_dbs/KEGG.txt \
  --bmr 8.7E-07


**REQUIRED ARGUMENTS**

  bam-list   Text
    Tab delimited list of BAM files [sample_name, normal_bam, tumor_bam] (See Description) 
  gene-covg-dir   Text
    Directory containing per-gene coverage files (Created using music bmr calc-covg) 
  maf-file   Text
    List of mutations using TCGA MAF specifications v2.3 
  output-file   Text
    Output file that will list the significant pathways and their p-values 
  pathway-file   Text
    Tab-delimited file of pathway information (See Description) 


**OPTIONAL ARGUMENTS**

  bmr   Number
    Background mutation rate in the targeted regions 
    Default value '1e-06' if not specified
  genes-to-ignore   Text
    Comma-delimited list of genes whose mutations should be ignored 
  min-mut-genes-per-path   Number
    Pathways with fewer mutated genes than this, will be ignored 
    Default value '1' if not specified


**DESCRIPTION**

    Only the following four columns in the MAF are used. All other columns may be left blank.

     Col 1: Hugo_Symbol (Need not be HUGO, but must match gene names used in the pathway file)
     Col 2: Entrez_Gene_Id (Matching Entrez ID trump gene name matches between pathway file and MAF)
     Col 9: Variant_Classification (PathScan ignores Silent|RNA|3'Flank|3'UTR|5'Flank|5'UTR|Intron)
     Col 16: Tumor_Sample_Barcode (Must match the name in sample-list, or contain it as a substring)

    The Entrez_Gene_Id can also be left blank (or set to 0), but it is highly recommended, in case
    genes are named differently in the pathway file and the MAF file.



**ARGUMENTS**


    --pathway-file

      This is a tab-delimited file prepared from a pathway database (such as KEGG), with the
      columns: [path_id, path_name, class, gene_line, diseases, drugs, description] The latter
      three columns are optional (but are available on KEGG). The gene_line contains the
      "entrez_id:gene_name" of all genes involved in this pathway, each separated by a "|" symbol.

	For example, a line in the pathway-file would look like:

          hsa00061      Fatty acid biosynthesis Lipid Metabolism        31:ACACA|32:ACACB|27349:MCAT|2194:FASN|54995:OXSM|55301:OLAH

	Ensure that the gene names and entrez IDs used match those used in the MAF file. Entrez IDs
	are not mandatory (use a 0 if Entrez ID unknown). But if a gene name in the MAF does not
	match any gene name in this file, the entrez IDs are used to find a match (unless it's a
	0).

    --gene-covg-dir

      This is usually the gene_covgs subdirectory created when you run "music bmr calc-covg". It
      should contain files for each sample that report per-gene covered base counts.

    --bam-list

      Provide a file containing sample names and normal/tumor BAM locations for each. Use the tab-
      delimited format [sample_name normal_bam tumor_bam] per line. This tool only needs
      sample_name, so all other columns can be skipped. The sample_name must be the same as the
      tumor sample names used in the MAF file (16th column, with the header Tumor_Sample_Barcode).

    --bmr

      The overall background mutation rate. This can be calculated using "music bmr calc-bmr".

    --genes-to-ignore

      A comma-delimited list of genes to ignore from the MAF file. This is useful when there are
      recurrently mutated genes like TP53 which might mask the significance of other genes.




    </help>
</tool>
