<tool id="gmt_music_smg" name="gmt_music_smg" version="0.3.0">
  <description>
    Identify significantly mutated genes.
  </description>
  <command>
    gmt music smg
    #if $bmr_modifier_file
      --bmr-modifier-file=$bmr_modifier_file
    #end if
    --gene-mr-file=$gene_mr_file
    --max-fdr=$max_fdr
    --output-file=$output_file
    --processors=$processors
    $skip_low_mr_genes
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="bmr_modifier_file" format="text" type="data" help="" optional="true"/>
    <param name="gene_mr_file" format="text" type="data" help="" />
    <param name="max_fdr" format="text" type="float" value="0.20" help="" />
    <param name="processors" format="text" type="integer" value="1" help="" />
    <param name="skip_low_mr_genes" format="text" help="" checked="False" truevalue="--skip-low-mr-genes" falsevalue="--noskip-low-mr-genes"/>

  </inputs>
  <outputs>
    <data name="output_file" format="text" label="" help="" />

  </outputs>
  <help>


    **USAGE**

    gmt music smg --gene-mr-file=? --output-file=? [--max-fdr=?] [--skip-low-mr-genes]
    [--bmr-modifier-file=?] [--processors=?]


    **SYNOPSIS**

    ... music smg \
    --gene-mr-file output_dir/gene_mrs \
    --output-file output_dir/smgs

    (A "gene-mr-file" can be generated using the tool "music bmr calc-bmr".)


    **REQUIRED ARGUMENTS**

    gene-mr-file
    File with per-gene mutation rates (Created using "music bmr calc-bmr") 
    output-file
    Output file that will list significantly mutated genes and their p-values 


    **OPTIONAL ARGUMENTS**

    max-fdr
    The maximum allowed false discovery rate for a gene to be considered an SMG 
    Default value '0.2' if not specified
    skip-low-mr-genes
    Skip testing genes with MRs lower than the background MR 
    Default value 'true' if not specified
    noskip-low-mr-genes
    Make skip-low-mr-genes 'false' 
    bmr-modifier-file
    Tab delimited multipliers per gene that modify BMR before testing [gene_name bmr_modifier] 
    processors
    Number of processors to use (requires 'foreach' and 'doMC' R packages) 
    Default value '1' if not specified


    **DESCRIPTION**

    This script runs R-based statistical tools to identify Significantly Mutated Genes (SMGs), when
    given per-gene mutation rates categorized by mutation type, and the overall background mutation
    rates (BMRs) for each of those categories (gene_mr_file, created using "music bmr calc-bmr").

    P-values and false discovery rates (FDRs) for each gene in gene_mr_file is calculated using
    three tests: Fisher's Combined P-value test (FCPT), Likelihood Ratio test (LRT), and the
    Convolution test (CT). For a gene, if its FDR for at least 2 of these tests is <= max_fdr, it
    will be output as an SMG. Another output file with prefix "_detailed" will have p-values and
    FDRs for all genes.



    **ARGUMENTS**


    --bmr-modifier-file

    The user can provide a BMR modifier for each gene in the ROI file, which is a multiplier for
    the categorized background mutation rates, before testing them against the gene's categorized
    mutation rates. Such a file can be used to correct for regional or systematic bias in
    mutation rates across the genome that may be correlated to CpG deamination or DNA repair
    processes like transcription-coupled repair or mismatch repair. Mutation rates have also been
    associated with DNA replication timing, where higher mutation rates are seen in late
    replicating regions. Note that the same per-gene multiplier is used on each mutation category
    of BMR. Any genes from the ROI file that are not in the BMR modifier file will be tested
    against unmodified overall BMRs per mutation category. BMR modifiers of <=0 are not
    permitted, because that's just silly.

    --skip-low-mr-genes

    Genes with consistently lower MRs than the BMRs across mutation categories, may show up in
    the results as an SMG (by CT or LRT). If such genes are not of interest, they may be assigned
    a p-value of 1. This should also speed things up. Genes with higher Indel or Truncation rates
    than the background will not be skipped even if the gene's overall MR is lower than the BMR.
    If bmr-modifiers are applied, this step uses the modified BMRs instead.




  </help>
</tool>
